LAXMIKANT LP PATHADE

http://laxmikantpathade.com • (315)560-8200 • lpathade@syr.edu 4-023, Center for Science and Technology, Syracuse University, Syracuse NY 13244

Profile

Resourceful materials researcher with 8+ years of training, 4+ years of facility administrator experience, exceptional workethic, team player with strong written and oral communications skills.

Skilled in materials research, wet-lab syntheses, structural characterization, electron microscopy, spectroscopy, computational analysis, technical softwares, & computers.

Work & Research Experience

X-ray Facility Administrator at Syracuse University

2014-present

- Trained new users on the diffractometer and necessary safety protocols; coordinated user queue.
- Collaborated with internal & external users for specialized sample prep & data analysis.
- Maintained auxiliary chiller operations & repaired minor breakdowns. Scheduled maintenance & regulatory inspections.

Graduate Researcher at Syracuse University

2013-present

- Published 6+ peer reviewed journal articles, co-authored 2 patents, and presented work in several professional conferences.
- Investigated synthetic design of transition metal nanoparticles (NPs) that exhibited hollow internal microstructures.
- Successfully exploited our findings to improve corrosion resistance in these NPs and create truly "stainless" nanoparticles.
- Explored other topics including asymmetric internal voids in novel NP systems, silica coating & surface functionalization of magnetic NPs, reaction monitoring using CsPbX₃ perovskites, & DDA computation routines.

Teaching Assistant at Syracuse University

2013-present

- Received the Graduate Teaching Mentor Award in 2015 from the graduate school at SU.
- Taught General Chemistry and Honors General Chemistry labs and lectures to 400+ undergrads over 4 years.
- Supervised several undergraduate trainees & summer REU researchers working in the Maye lab.
- Developed 4 new lab modules to introduce advanced materials chemistry topics such as synthesis & properties of NPs.

Industrial Internships

- Executed a synthesis scale-up & technology transfer project for a Fortune 500 chemical company in record time. 2017
- Interned at 2 medium-sized pigment-manufacturing plants in the Mumbai industrial area. Reviewed unit operations of chemical engineering, and authored a report on manufacturing efficiency & workplace safety.

 2012

EDUCATION

Syracuse University 2013-2018

Ph.D. Candidate in *Materials Chemistry* with Prof. Mathew M. Maye

Thesis: Internal Morphology & Corrosion Resistance in Stainless Steel Nanoparticles

Institute of Chemical Technology, Mumbai

2009-2013

B.Tech. in Organic Colorant Technology; Minors in Chemical Engineering

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Synthesis: Nanoparticles (Transition and Noble Metals, Perovskites, Quantum Dots) · Air-free Techniques (Schlenk Line and Glovebox) · Microwave · Organic Lab work
- Structural Characterization: Powder and Single Crystal X-ray Diffraction (Currently work as facility admin)
- Electron Microscopy: TEM / HR-TEM (trained on 3 different JEOL TEMs; trained new users) equipped with EDS & STEM detectors · SEM (JEOL IT100LA) · AFM (Bruker Innova) · Optical
- Spectroscopy: X-Ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy (XPS/ESCA) · Energy Dispersive X-ray Spectroscopy (EDS Certification from Oxford Instruments) · NMR · Raman · Mass-Spec · FTIR · UV-Vis · Photoluminescence (PL)
- Technical Misc.: Magnetization in materials · Cyclic Voltammetry · Dynamic Light Scattering (DLS)- ζ potential · Ultracentrifuge · Spin & Sputter coater · Photolithography · Thermo-gravimetric analysis (TGA) · DSC · Vernier Modules
- Computational Analysis: Discrete Dipole Approximation (DDA) · Familiar with FDTD
- $\bullet \ \, \textbf{Softwares} \colon \ \, \text{Origin} \cdot \text{Plotly} \cdot \text{ImageJ} \cdot \text{ChemDraw} \cdot \text{Vesta} \cdot \text{TEMCON (JEOL)} \cdot \text{Digital Micrograph (Gatan)} \cdot \text{AZtec (Oxford Instruments)} \cdot \text{Bruker Diffrac.Suite} \cdot \text{CasaXPS} \cdot \text{Adobe Illustrator} \cdot \text{Corel-Draw} \cdot \text{Maya (basics)} \cdot \text{Tinkercad}$
- Languages & Computer Misc.: Python · Jekyll · Wordpress · HTML · 3D-printing · Raspberry Pi · git · IATEX